我 的 父 亲 母 亲
本片改编自鲍十所著小说“纪念”
父亲突然去世了
My father died suddenly.
我是昨天晚上知道的
I only found out last night.
村长给我打了一个长途电话
The mayor called to tell me.
当时我真不敢相信
I couldn't believe it.
我的家在山区  一个不大的村子
My hometown is in the mountains...
叫三合屯
a village called Sanhetun.
我很早就离开家乡出来工作了
I left to work in the city.
因为忙  几年都回不了一次家
I'm so busy I haven't been home in years.
父亲是村里的小学老师
My father was the village schoolteacher.
在当地教了一辈子书
He taught there all his life.
我是父母唯一的孩子
I am an only child.
也是村里唯一念过大学的
The only one from our village who went to college.
我现在最担心的就是母亲  怕她一下子受不了
I am very worried about my mother.
师傅  进屋喝口水歇会儿吧
Come in and rest a while.
不了  我还要赶紧回去呢
I've got to get back.
那回去跟你们老总说  回头我当面谢他
Thank your boss again for me.
- 不客气    - 谢谢啊
- Thank you.    - Goodbye.
妈
Mother?
生子
Yusheng.
村长  夏大叔
Mayor, Uncle Xia.
在外头看见车  才知道你回来了
I saw the car and knew you were back.
那进屋吧
Come in.
屋里暖和
It's warmer inside.
你也坐  坐吧
Please. Sit down.
给你去个电话  说情况也没说清楚
I couldn't tell you much over the phone.
这次你回来呀  给你说一说
Now you're here, I can explain everything.
咱村里这个学校啊
It's the schoolhouse.
你爸是早就要求要翻盖  多少年了吧
For many years your father has wanted to rebuild it,
因为村里困难  也没答应
but there were always reasons we couldn't.
现在你爸又张罗要翻盖学校
He brought it up again recently,
村里这回就决定要翻盖学校
and the village agreed.
可是木料都预备够了  还缺钱
We have the materials we need but not enough money.
没钱他就急了
Your father's mind was set.
他着急啊  他就赶着出去借
He was determined to find the money.
关于你爸借钱  可跑了多少趟
He began traveling around, trying to borrow the money.
这儿  那儿  凡是他不错的
He went all over the county.
有词儿的人
If he thought there was a chance,
他都张罗去借去
he'd go after it.
结果呢  这趟回来
On the last trip, on his way home...
在路中就给赶上了风雪  特别大
he ran into a snowstorm, a big blizzard.
就给激了  激病了
He was stuck in the storm, and he got sick.
这两天白毛风
He was too sick to be moved.
激病了
That made him more anxious.
激病了回来一看不行了
He was in bad shape when he got back,
这就送到县城医院经过了看
so we took him to the hospital.
这一看啊  是心脏病
They examined him, said he had a heart problem.
咱们你说老哥在这儿多少年
We've known your dad all these years.
不知道他有心脏病  结果呢  是心脏病
Who knew he had a heart condition?
治疗了  看了不行
They tried treating him, but it was no use.
这就结果呢  你爸也就不顶了
He fought, but he didn't make it.
我爸在哪儿呢
Where is my father now?
现在在县医院呢  在太平房
At the provincial hospital, in the morgue.
这不就等着你回来
That's why we wanted you to return.
跟你商量
To tell you all this.
上次通电话的时候还挺好  咋整的呢
Last time I spoke with him, he seemed fine.
就是年纪大了  再赶上风雪
It was a bad storm.
人上岁数  再赶上这大雪天  大白毛风
At his age, it was too much for him.
这一激  受不了啦
It would have been
人是不顶了
hard on anyone.
我们村的意思呢  是打算明天待一天
The village wants to arrange a car
后天咱们用车给他接回来
to bring your father back.
- 已经三天了    - 在咱们村给他安葬就得了
- It's been three days.    - Bring him back here to bury him.
大概就这个意思
That's what we planned.
那就按村长的意思办吧  我没啥意见
That's fine. Go ahead.
没啥意见  还有一个问题
But there is a problem.
这问题就是你妈不同意拿车拉
Your mother doesn't want to use a car.
她要求是抬回来
She wants your father to be carried back.
抬是啥意思啊
What do you mean?
抬就是  按老迷信说就是  再返回来走走老路
She wants the coffin brought back on foot...
回来看看这个老路  就是别忘这个老路吧
so your father won't forget his way home.
- 这是老一套迷信    - 那我妈是这么想的吗
- It's an old tradition, a superstition.    - I see.
她还想陪着也走回来跟着
And she wants to walk with us.
那就抬
So let's do it.
抬呢  咱们村里也同意
We want to.
在这教了多少年学了  要说抬  也没问题
He was our village teacher. Everyone respects him.
实际上咱们村子里  现在是年轻人都走光了
But our young people have all left for the city.
都在外面做活
They've gone away to work.
尽剩些老的老小的小
Only old people and children are left.
村里的意思是想用拖拉机
We thought of using a tractor.
半天也就拉回来了
We could make the trip in half a day.
这回让你回来做做你妈的工作
You must help your mother decide.
行  大爷  你们别为难
I appreciate your concern.
这事儿我跟我妈说说  劝劝她
I will talk it over with her.
- 对    - 唉  我妈呢
- Good.    - Where is she?
你爸死了她就上那学校坐着
Probably at the schoolhouse.
一到学校就发呆坐着  谁劝也不行
She's there every day since he died.
- 谁劝也不回来    - 她这一坐就是半天
- She won't listen to anyone.    - She just sits there.
- 没啥事儿吧    - 没啥事儿
- Is she okay?    - I think so.
就怕她也
I am only afraid--
是不是以前那学校啊
The old schoolhouse?
就是以前的学校
Yes.
那我过去看看
I'll go to her.
- 妈    - 生儿
- Mother.    - Yusheng.
天这么冷  咱们回家去吧
It's so cold. Let's go home, okay?
你爸不在了
Your father is dead.
走  咱们回家  妈
Let's go home.
再也看不着你爸了
You will never see him again.
妈  上炕暖和暖和吧
Get on the bed where it's warm.
生子  你跟我搬织布机去
Yusheng. Bring me my loom.
织布机  搬它干啥  妈
What for?
我要织布
I want to weave something.
织啥布
Weave what?
我要给你爸织块挡棺布
A cloth for your father's coffin.
妈  你看这样行不行
Don't trouble yourself.
咱们别织了  我上供销社给你买一块
Why don't we go buy one instead?
买的我不要
I don't want to buy one.
织布机都几十年了
That loom is so old.
早都坏了  再说现在谁还自己织布呢
It's been broken for years.
坏了  叫你夏大叔修修嘛
Why can't we fix it?
我看  妈
You need rest, Mother.
这两天你这身体也是太累了
You must be so tired.
那我也得亲手给他织一块挡棺
I have to make this cloth.
我现在就给您买去  行吗
Can't I just buy one?
买的我不要  我叫你搬你就搬
No, just bring me the loom.
咱们村子里  根本就没有织布机了
The only loom left in the village...
你妈呀  还留这么一个
his this one of your mother's.
当宝贝似的留着
She's guarded it like a treasure.
看起来呀  你妈要织布  修的这个织布机要织布
Looks like she's determined to use it.
那就是要抬了
Just like the funeral procession.
抬的意思也就是过去那么个老习惯
Carrying the dead is an old custom.
什么过个山了
Over the mountains...
过个沟了  过个路口了
across the river, past the crossroads.
这就喊着点
And we shout at him along the way.
就喊点什么呢  什么意思呢
What do we say?
就是走这儿  叫他记住这个道儿
We tell him this is the road home.
大伙在这喊着点
Everyone yells at him,
叫他记住这个道儿
so that he remembers his way home.
就这么个意思
It's an old tradition.
夏大叔  我想问问
Is it really so difficult
要是非抬不可的话  咱村里确实有困难  真抬不了
to do as my mother wishes?
咱们村里确实有困难
It is a problem, yes.
这个没有劳力
We don't have the manpower.
劳力都出去了  加了就是老的老小的小了
All our young people have left.
抬回来  那都是文化大革命以前的事儿了
No one has followed this custom...
现在谁抬你  确实在没有人
since the Cultural Revolution.
我真不想让母亲织这块布
I don't want her to work like this...
可我不知道怎样劝她
but I don't know how to stop her.
把父亲抬回来
The funeral procession...
似乎是母亲现在唯一的想法
seems all that matters to her now.
妈  听老村长说  您想把爸抬回来
Mother, I know about your wishes for the funeral.
是的
Yes.
我是想  挺麻烦的  要不然就再想个办法
Is there some other way to arrange it?
你别替他们操心麻烦
I know it won't be easy.
你看你爸到这村四十多年
But your father lived here for 40 years.
为这个学校  给他们培养出多少左一代右一代的学生
He taught many generations of kids.
起早睡晚的  心都操碎了
He worked very hard. Long, long hours.
咱们就这么点事儿  他们给咱们讲出这么些困难
The town should give him something back.
那村长倒是没有别的意思
The mayor agrees with you.
他就说了个困难
How about this?
我是觉得吧  妈  你说拿人抬回来
We can walk alongside...
和拖拉机拉回来  不是都一样吗
with the coffin pulled by a tractor.
不都是接我爸回来
We'd still be with him, right?
这个就不一样
It's not the same.
怎么也得找人去
I want your father carried back...
把你爸一块儿接回来
by the men.
再不成  他们有困难  咱们想办法
If they won't help...
咱们去人  一块儿把你爸接回来
we'll get someone who will.
你今天晚上就别织了  行吗
Please don't work anymore.
这块布  我非得一定要把它织完了
I have to. I have to finish it.
你累好几天了  你休息休息吧  行吗
You are tired. Get some rest, okay?
你上你爸上课那屋睡觉吧
You sleep in your father's study.
我今天还非得把它织出来
I have to finish this.
这张照片  还是父亲和母亲结婚那年照的
This picture was taken the year my parents married.
父亲原本不是我们三合屯的人
My father was not from the village.
他是后来才来的
He came here to teach.
当年父亲和母亲谈恋爱的事儿
The story of my parents' courtship...
曾经轰动一时
is well-known in the village.
村里人说来说去的  听起来都像个故事
Practically everyone here has heard about it.
那年母亲刚满十八岁
My mother had just turned 18.
父亲也只有二十岁
My father was 20.
听母亲说
My mother told me
是一辆马车把父亲拉到了三合屯
my father arrived by horse cart.
驾
Yah!
这就是来咱们三合屯教书的先生
This is our new teacher, Mr. Luo.
- 姓骆  叫骆长余    - 别叫先生  叫老师就行了
- His name is Luo, Luo Changyu.    - Just call me Luo.
是娣儿呀
Is that Di?
慌慌张张的干啥呢
What's all the racket for?
没干啥
Nothing.
今儿一大早闹闹轰轰的  都说是去看先生  先生来了吗
Has the teacher arrived?
来了
Yes.
这多好  咱们三合屯  总算也有了先生了
It's about time we got our own teacher.
那先生是啥样啊
What does he look like?
是个小伙子
He's a young man.
小伙子  小伙子就当先生了
A young teacher?
这小伙子倒真能耐
He must be talented.
那他住哪儿呀
Where is he staying?
村政府吧
At the village council office.
村政府倒也行
That's good.
那东屋有铺炕  吃饭呢
Where will he eat?
吃派饭  一家一天轮着吃
He'll eat with a different family each day.
那也该派到咱家
When it's our turn,
到时候啊  可得给先生吃饱喽
we'll have to make a good meal.
娣儿  你在干啥呢
What are you doing?
没干啥
Nothing.
看先生就看先生
Seeing a teacher
还换什么新衣裳
has you changing clothes?
姥姥的眼睛那时候已经瞎了
My grandmother was already blind by then.
听母亲说  是姥爷死的时候
Mother says when Grandfather died...
姥姥天天哭  把眼睛给哭坏了
Grandmother cried until she went blind.
姥爷死后
After Grandfather died,
家里就没有其他人了  就母亲陪着姥姥
there was only Mother to look after Grandmother.
姥姥一门心思
Grandmother's only wish
想给母亲找个好婆家
was to find a good husband for Mother.
提亲的人倒是很多
She had many proposals...
母亲一个都没看上
but my mother didn't like any of them.
父亲已经来了
The schoolhouse was not yet built
村里的学校还没有盖好
when my father arrived.
那几天  村长正领着乡亲们赶着盖
The mayor enlisted all the men's help.
照我们当地的习俗
According to our village custom...
新房盖好的时候
a red cloth must be hung in a new building.
都要在梁上裹一块红布  图个吉利
It's hung on the ceiling beam for good luck.
这块布就叫红
The cloth is called the lucky red banner.
通常是由
It must be woven
村里最漂亮的姑娘来织
by the village's most beautiful maiden.
这次织红的事儿  自然又落在了我母亲的身上
This task, of course, fell to my mother.
也许是因为心里有了父亲的原因吧
Perhaps she was already a little in love...
这块红  母亲织得格外仔细
because the cloth she made was especially fine.
当年村里有两口井
The village had two wells back then.
以前的井叫前井
The old well was called the "front well."
后来新打的那口井叫后井
The newer well was called the "back well."
后井近
The new well was nearer the village,
人们通常都在后井打水
so more people used that one.
自从父亲来了以后
After my father arrived...
母亲就改在前井打水了
Mother started to use the old well.
因为这样会路过学校
She had to pass the schoolhouse to get to it.
照那时候的规矩
The village had another custom.
凡是盖房这类大事儿
When putting up a new building,
家家户户都要往工地上送饭  给干活儿的男人吃
each family prepared a dish for the workers' lunch.
这叫送公饭
Everyone contributed.
那几天  母亲尽挑好吃的做
Mother prepared all her best dishes,
她总希望父亲能吃上她亲手做的饭
hoping Father would eat what she made.
听母亲说  以前有挺多事儿  女人都不能上前
Back then when something was built...
比方说盖房子  还有打井这种大事儿
women were not allowed to participate.
说怕沾上邪气儿
Superstition said they would bring bad luck.
所以现在盖学校
When they put up the school,
村里的妇女们就只能离得远远的
the village women could only watch
在一边看
from a distance.
大姐  今天你送的什么饭呀
What did you make today?
馒头和烙饼
Steamed bread.
招娣  你送的什么饭
What about you, Di?
我送葱油饼
I made onion cakes.
你送葱油饼  我送苞米碴干饭
I brought rice steamed in lotus leaves.
苞米碴干饭可没有葱油饼好吃
Onion cakes are better.
你留什么好吃的  晚上偷着给你男人吃呢
Did you save some for your boyfriend?
你胡说
Shut up!
你没看见吗
Look at them.
他们都是乱吃
They just pick up the first dish they see.
谁也不知道谁吃的谁家的
They don't know who made what.
我送的包子不知道谁吃了
I don't know who's eating mine.
让你男人吃了
Must be your husband!
放着吧
Put them here.
招娣  你把红给送来了
You're already done with the banner?
我还正要到你家去取呢
I was going to come get it from you.
给我  给我啊
Give it to me.
行  行  给你
Okay.
还省得我给你去送呢
You'll save me a further trip.
招娣  你这红织得可真好
This is a beautiful banner.
过两天一上梁  学校盖好了  就能上课了
The school is almost finished.
先生说  第一天上语文
Chinese study will be the first lesson.
那先生这两天吃得好不好
Is the teacher happy with the food?
好啊
Yes.
他也跟着吃公饭
Does he eat what we make?
是啊
Yes.
那他也抢着吃
He eats together with you?
哪能呐  人家是城里来的文化人
No. He's a city gentleman.
不能和咱们一块抢着吃
It's not proper for him to eat with us.
那他咋吃的
So how does it work?
每次都是紧着先生端头一份儿
We give him first pick of the dishes.
人生在世  念
"In life--" Follow me.
人生在世
"In life--"
要有志气  念
"You must make goals."
要有志气
好  咱们再读第二遍
Start from the beginning.
读书识字  多长见识  念
"One must learn to write." Follow me.
读书识字  多长见识
"One must learn to write."
能写会算  是件好事  念
"One must learn arithmetic."
能写会算  是件好事
大事小情  提笔就记  念
"Keep a journal faithfully."
大事小情  提笔就记
知今知古  知天知地  念
"Know the present, know the past."
知今知古  知天知地
小时候听母亲说起过
When I was young, my mother told me
父亲念书的声音特别好听
my father had a beautiful voice.
母亲不识字
My mother never learned to write,
有的课文她也听不懂
was never interested in school.
但是她觉得父亲的声音是天底下最好听的声音
But she couldn't resist the sound of my father's voice.
从这一天开始  母亲就天天去听
She went by the school every day after that.
后来村里人习惯了  就没人再去听了
For most, the novelty of the new school wore off after a while...
可是母亲还是去听
but not for my mother.
她一听就听了四十多年
For 40 years, she came to listen...
这已经成了她生活中的一部分
and it became part of her life.
长幼尊卑  敬重有序  念
"Know respect for your elders."
长幼尊卑  敬重有序
母亲听说每天放学的时候
Each day after school...
父亲都要送几个路远的孩子回家
my father walked some of his students home.
她就动了心思  想在那条路上碰见父亲
Knowing this, my mother waited along the way.
太阳光  金亮亮  雄鸡唱三唱
♪ The birds sing with the beautiful sun ♪
花儿醒来了  鸟儿忙梳妆
♪ Their songs wake the beautiful flowers ♪
嘿
Hey!
她是谁呀
Who is she?
她是老田家的招娣
That's Zhao Di.
那她是咱三合屯的人吗
Is she from Sanhetun?
住在后街那儿
Yes.
招娣姐  我们老师问你呢
Di, the teacher is asking about you!
先生  挑水去
You need water?
唉
Yes.
来来来  我帮你挑
Let me get it for you.
不用  我自己来
No, that's okay.
我来我来
Let me do it.
不  不  不  没事儿  没事儿
I can do it. Thanks.
你客气什么嘛  这活儿我们都干惯了
No, let me. Let me help you!
您是教书的  您怎么能干这活呢
You're the teacher. You shouldn't bother.
我来  我来
Let me do it.
不用  我自己来就行
No, no.
不行  不行
Come on.
我行
Let me do it.
招娣  你咋跑前井打水来啦
Di, you're fetching water as well?
明天该轮到我家吃饭了
Tomorrow it's our turn to have you over.
我知道
I know.
父亲对我说过
My father told me...
他第一次到母亲家吃派饭的时候
the first time he went to my mother's house,
母亲站在门口迎他
she stood in the doorway.
他记得母亲扶着门框  站在门口的样子
Leaning against the door frame...
就像一幅画
she looked like a figure in a painting...
他说很多年他都忘不了这幅画
an image he would never forget.
娣儿  是先生来了吧
Is the teacher here?
来了
Yes.
我就说嘛  这脚步声这么重
Your heavy footsteps gave you away.
快到屋里来  我看看
Come in. Come here.
我娘的眼睛坏了
My mother's eyesight is not good.
噢
Oh.
这先生这么高啊
This teacher is very tall.
坐下  坐下
Sit down.
上炕吧
Please!
家里多少年没有男人吃饭了
Can't think when we last had a man home for dinner.
听听  吃得真香啊
The food must taste good to you.
嚼得多有劲啊
You sound like you're enjoying it.
先生来咱们三合屯有一个月了吧
How long have you been here?
一个多月了
About a month.
还待得惯吗
Have you gotten used to it?
待得惯
It's okay.
待得惯就好
That's good.
先生家在县上住
You're from the city?
县上东关
Yes, from East Gate.
那咋来三合屯呢
How did you choose Sanhetun?
学校毕业  在家没事儿
After graduation, I couldn't find work.
在县上乱逛  看见敲锣打鼓的  喊人报名
One day in the street, a man was signing people up.
也不知道干啥的  没仔细问  我就报了一个
I didn't know what for, but I signed up anyway.
这不就来了
And I ended up here.
那不后悔
Do you regret it?
不后悔
No.
为啥
Why?
我喜欢
I like it here.
先生还没成家
Are you married?
没呢
No.
也没定亲
Are you engaged?
没呢
No.
你别管  让招娣收拾  坐着  歇会儿
Di will do it. Sit for a while.
你认得我家的碗吗
Do you remember this bowl?
就这青花的
This design?
我不认得
No, I don't remember.
你吃没吃公饭
Did you eat the food brought to the site?
吃了
Yes.
这可真是瞎了招娣的一片心了
Looks like Di's hard work was wasted.
别看都不说  我可都知道  盖学堂  吃公饭
You know when you were building the school,
她是调着样儿做好的
she made all her best dishes.
回回都拿这青花碗送过去
She always used that bowl,
就指盼着先生能吃上一口
hoping you would choose her dish.
连我都不让动上一筷子
Even I wasn't allowed to help.
噢  吃公饭啊  这碗我还真使过
I remember now.
你使过
You do?
我说嘛  有点眼熟  使过
The bowl and your cooking are familiar.
碗里的饭你也吃了
So you ate from it before?
吃了
Yes.
你说  都吃啥了
You did? What did you eat?
呃
Uh...
我跟你说  我头一天送的是葱花油饼
On the first day, I made onion cakes.
第二天  送的是小米饭  葱花炒鸡蛋
On the second, scrambled eggs and onions on rice.
第三天  送的是蘑菇馅蒸饺
On the third day, mushroom dumplings.
真可惜啦  这么好吃的三顿饭
What a shame. Three delicious meals.
蘑菇馅蒸饺我最爱吃了
And I love mushroom dumplings.
那你后晌来  我给你做
I'll make you some this afternoon.
太麻烦了
That is too much to ask.
不麻烦
No.
这刚吃了前晌
You've hardly finished lunch,
就惦着后晌了
and you're planning the next meal.
招娣  送先生走  先生还忙着呢
Di, show the teacher out. He must be very busy.
对  我该走了
Yes, I should go.
你穿那件红衣裳真好看
That red jacket of yours is pretty on you.
来的头一天我就看见了
I remember it from the day I arrived.
- 后晌你一定要来吃饺子    - 唉
- Don't forget to come back for dumplings.    - Okay.
我说  就别包那饺子了
You shouldn't make the dumplings.
为啥不包
Why not?
免得后悔
You may regret it.
我悔啥
Why?
悔啥你自己知道
You don't understand.
那先生  好是好
This teacher is a nice man,
他跟咱不是一路人  这事儿不成
but he's out of our class.
有啥成不成的  不就吃顿饺子吗
What are you talking about? It's only dumplings.
你别给我装糊涂
Don't play dumb.
我把话给你撂下
I'm just being honest.
你就死了这心吧
You'd best forget about him.
我不回去就是不回去
I will not go back!
你别无选择
You've got no choice!
我来跟你说一声  我要走了
I came to say goodbye.
走  走哪儿啊
Where are you going?
我回县里面
Back to the city.
啥事儿这么急
What's happened?
没啥事儿
Nothing.
我在井台上看到他跟你吵架了
I saw you argue with someone.
是他叫你回去的
Was that what it was about?
他是谁呀  你回去干啥
Who was he? Why do you have to go back?
真没啥事儿
It's no big deal.
他们是有事儿问我  问完就完了呗
They just want to ask me some questions. That's all.
那在这儿不能问
Can't they ask you questions here?
他做不了主
He says it's not up to him.
那你还回来吗
Will you come back?
回来  我一定回来  学生们等我上课呢
Of course. I have classes to teach.
那你啥时候回来
When will you be back?
最晚  腊月初八我一定回来
By the 27th at the latest.
腊月初九  学生放假
On the 28th, the school holiday starts.
我得在放假前回来
I have to be back before that.
进屋吃饺子吧
Come in and eat something.
饺子恐怕吃不了了
I can't.
还有事儿呢  你和你娘就别等了
I have things to do before I go.
真还有事儿呢  他等着我呢
I really do. That man is waiting for me.
那你招呼他一块儿来吃吧
Tell him to come too.
啥要紧事儿也得先吃饭呐
You have to eat in any case.
行  我来吃
Okay, I'll be back.
那我等着你
I'll wait for you.
这个是我给你买的
This is for you.
配你那件红衣裳  好看
To go with your red jacket.
那我等着你啊
I'll be waiting.
唉
Okay.
到底咋回事儿啊  这不正上课着吗
What is going on? No more class?
说是要让他当个右派
He's in some political trouble.
啥派
Political trouble?
我也整不明白  反正没啥大事儿
I don't understand it either. But maybe it's nothing.
说不定过两天就回来了
Said he might be back in a day or two.
先生走了
The teacher's left.
先生走了吗
The teacher's left?
走了
Yes.
他走了
Just left?
刚刚村长他们把他送走
Just left with the mayor.
母亲一连好几天早出晚归
My mother retraced her steps every day...
她把那几十里山路都跑遍了
searching back and forth.
她想找到父亲留给她的那支发夹
She had to find the clip my father had given her.
修碗  修盆
Pottery repairs!
锔碗的
锔碗的  进来
Please come in.
我是照钉收钱的
I charge for the nails I use.
这比买一个新碗可贵多了
This will cost you more than buying a new bowl.
该多少钱给多少钱  分文不短你的
Just tell me how much, and I'll pay you.
是祖上传下来的吗
Is it a family heirloom?
倒也不是
No.
那就是有人使过
It belonged to someone special?
算你说对了  有人使过
You could say that.
谁使过
Who?
不瞒你说  我这是替闺女锔的
It's for my daughter.
使碗的人走了  把闺女的心也带走了
The man who used it left
把这碗锔好了  也给闺女留个念
and took my daughter's heart with him.
我给你把它锔得滴水不漏
I've put it back together again.
保准给你闺女一个好念想
I hope she'll be happy.
修碗  修盆
Pottery repairs!
娣儿  你干啥呢
Di, what are you doing?
没干啥  我舀口水喝
Nothing. Just getting a drink of water.
一八得八
1 times 8 equals 8.
一九得九
1 times 9 equals 9.
二二得四
2 times 2 equals 4.
二三得六
2 times 3 equals 6.
二四得八
2 times 4 equals 8.
二五一十
2 times 5 equals 10.
二六一十二
2 times 6 equals 12.
二七一十四
2 times 7 equals 14.
二八一十六
2 times 8 equals 16.
二九一十八
2 times 9 equals 18.
好
Good.
三三得九
3 times 3 equals 9.
三四一十二
3 times 4 equals 12.
三五一十五
3 times 5 equals 15.
三六一十八
3 times 6 equals 18.
三七二十一
3 times 7 equals 21.
三八二十四
3 times 8 equals 24.
三九二十七
3 times 9 equals 27.
父亲对母亲说过
My father told my mother
他给学生上课的时候
when he was teaching the kids,
一抬眼就能看见梁上那块红
he could always look up and see the red banner.
一看见那红
When he saw that banner
就想起母亲穿红棉袄的样子
it reminded him of Mother and her red jacket.
后来村长说过好几次
The mayor kept insisting
要给教室吊个顶棚
that the ceiling needed proper insulation,
都被父亲谢绝了
but my father never let him.
所以我们村的这个小学校  几十年来就一直没有顶棚
That's why the school ceiling was never completed.
那天母亲在教室里一直坐到很晚
Mother sat in the classroom for hours that day.
教室门开着  被村长看见了
The door was open, and the mayor saw her there.
村长这才明白了母亲的心思
He understood what that meant.
村长知道了
Once he knew,
村里人很快也都知道了
the news got around the village, quickly.
在当年
Back then, arranged matches were the rule.
自由恋爱还是一件很新鲜的事儿
The freedom of falling in love was unfamiliar.
母亲给三合屯开了个头
This was a first for our village.
到了父亲答应回来的日子
On the day my father promised to return...
母亲一大早就站在那条路上等
my mother was waiting from first light.
她记着父亲说过的那句话
She remembered his promise:
腊月初八一定回来
that he would return on the 27th.
因为腊月初九学校就放假了
School vacation began on the 28th.
父亲得在放假前赶回来
He had to be back before that.
看这身寒气  干啥去了  一天不着家
It's so cold out. Where have you been?
快上炕躺会儿
Gone all day. Get warm on the bed.
这么烫  娣儿  你病了
You're burning up!
我知道你昨天迎先生去了
I know you went to wait for the teacher.
村里的人都说  先生犯了错误  回不来了
Everyone says he's in trouble and won't be back.
你就别操这份心了
You've got to let go.
我到县上找他去
I'm going to the city to find him.
你疯了  你还病着呢  你上县上咋找
Are you crazy?! You're ill!
娣儿  你回来  回来
Di! Come back!
那天母亲没走到县城
My mother didn't make it to the city.
却晕倒在半路上
She fainted by the road.
有过路人看见  给村里捎了信儿
Someone saw her, and they got word to the mayor.
村长和夏大叔他们套上马车  连夜把母亲拉了回来
The mayor and my uncle brought her home on a cart.
我记得村长后来跟我说过一次
The mayor said that day,
说那天母亲的两手冰凉冰凉的
my mother's hands were like ice.
在马车上
While on the cart,
他用皮袄暖了一路
they wrapped her in a heavy blanket,
都没暖过来
but they couldn't get her hands warm.
不要紧  冻着了
I don't think it's too serious.
虚火上升  气血淤滞  歇两天就好了
It's a bad chill, but she is strong.
村长  你说说  这先生到底还能不能回来
Mayor, is the teacher coming back?
这城里人的事儿  我也整不清楚
I don't know the answer.
照理说  他也该早回来了
He should have been back by now.
你们有谁方便啊  就给先生捎个信
Maybe someone can write to him.
他不回来  招娣咋办  我也拦不住她呀
I don't know how to help her...
就让先生回来呀  看上她一眼也好啊
if he doesn't come back.
春天来了
"Spring is here."
春风吹化了冰雪
"It melts the snow."
吹绿了草地
"The grass turns green."
农民在种庄稼
"The farmers sow."
牛在耕田
"The ox plow the field."
大雁回来了
"The wild geese return."
青蛙结束了冬眠
"The frogs begin to hop."
娣儿  你醒了
Di, you're awake.
你都睡了两天了
You've been sleeping for two days.
你还不知道呢
Di, the teacher is back.
先生回来了
The teacher is back.
先生昨晚就回来了
He came back yesterday.
一回来就上咱们家来了
He came straight here.
就在这儿守了你半宿
He sat with you for a long time.
娣儿  这下可好了  先生回来了
Isn't it good news?
他这是为你回来的呀
He came back for you.
充满勃勃的生机
"Full of energy."
我们的心情也跟万物一样
"Our spirit comes alive."
充满新的希望
"It carries our wishes."
充满新的理想
"Full of hope."
春天来了
"Spring is here."
春风吹化了冰雪
"It melts the snow."
吹绿了草地
"The grass turns green."
农民在种庄稼
"The farmers sow."
牛在耕田
"The ox plow the field."
大雁飞来了
"The wild geese return."
青蛙结束了冬眠
"The frogs begin to hop."
小燕子在欣喜地喳喳叫
"Swallows start to sing."
春天是播种的季节
"Spring is the season to sow."
万物都在生长
"All starts to grow again."
充满勃勃的生机
"The world is full of life again."
骆先生
Mr. Luo!
骆先生  招娣来看你了
Mr. Luo, Di is here to see you!
先生  先生
Sir!
招娣来了
Di is here!
天黑前  刚刚回来的父亲就又被叫走了
That evening, my father had to leave again.
因为他是偷着跑回来的
When he heard about my mother, he left the city...
他是听说了母亲的情况后
without permission.
实在忍不住
He couldn't stand it any longer,
就私自跑回来了
so he sneaked back.
由于父亲的这次行为
For this disobedience,
使他和母亲最后见面的日子又推迟了好几年
my parents were kept apart for another two years.
后来  我听乡亲们说
Someone told me,
当父亲真正和母亲相聚的那一天到来时
that on the day my father finally returned,
母亲又特意穿上了那件
my mother put on her red jacket,
父亲喜爱的红棉袄
my father's favorite,
站在路边等着父亲
and stood by the road to wait for him.
从那天起  父亲就再没离开过母亲一步
From that day on, my father never left my mother again.
这就是父亲和母亲的故事
This is the story of my father and my mother.
他们相识  相爱的过程  都和这条路有关
This road is part of their love story...
这是我们村通往县城的一条普通的山路
this road that leads from the city to our village.
也许就因为母亲曾经那么殷切
Maybe because of the hope it held for her
那么长久地在这条路上等待过父亲
as she waited for my father to return,
所以她还想陪着父亲  再从这条路上走回来
she wants to walk this way with him one last time.
村长
Mr. Mayor?
谁呀
Who is it?
我  生子
It's me, Yusheng.
- 生子  有事儿吗    - 有事儿
- You need to see me?    - Yes.
有事儿快进屋说  来  天挺冷的
Come in, come in. It's cold out there.
有什么事儿啊
How can I help you?
我妈的心思啊  我想明白了
I've thought it through.
咱们还是抬吧
I want to do as my mother wishes.
你也要抬
To carry him back?
可是咱们村还有点困难
It's still a problem, though.
不就是人手不够吗
The problem is not enough men, right?
你看这样行不行  村长
How about this:
咱们到邻村雇点人来
We'll hire men from the next village.
雇人  邻村倒是好雇
That's a good idea.
现在就这钱
But how do we pay them?
那没关系  您帮我算算得多少人
Just tell me how many men we need.
人嘛  要是近点  有十几多个人就够
For a short distance, only 10,
因为咱们这儿离县城太远
but this is a long trip.
这个你必须得十六个人的杠子
I think we need about 16.
得两班  两班就得三十二个
We will need two shifts. That's 32 men.
三十二个呢  再有几个闲人  拿凳子放在路中
And we'll need others to carry chairs,
有的人累了  可以搁上歇歇
so people can rest along the way.
这总共得个三十五六个人吧
That comes to about 35, 36 men.
那一个人得多少钱呢
How much per person?
一个人  现在咱就给他一百块钱
One hundred yuan each should do.
就可以了
That will do.
三十五六个人
Thirty-five, 36 people.
那你给算算总共得多少钱
How much in total?
人嘛  三十五六个人  三千五六百块钱
That's 3500 or 3600 yuan.
下来呀  有抽烟的  咱们还要给他买点烟
We need to buy cigarettes.
有喝酒的  这酒我也得买点  因为天太冷
And wine too, gotta ward off the cold.
要有点什么事儿  都得用点钱
We'll also want a little extra for emergency use.
可能有四千多块钱  就差不多了
Altogether, around 4000 yuan.
村长  这是五千块钱  够不够
Here's 5000 yuan. Is that enough?
足够了  用不了
It's more than enough.
老嫂子  去看看骆先生吧
Mrs. Luo, come and see Mr. Luo.
去看的时候可别哭
Please don't cry.
别让眼泪掉在骆先生身上  不好的
Don't let tears fall on him.
骆先生  咱们现在回村了  要走好
Mr. Luo, we are going back to the village.
那天抬棺来了一百多个人
That day over 100 people came to the ceremony.
听村长说  他们都是父亲的学生
The mayor told me they were my father's students.
他们知道了这件事情  就都赶来了
They heard about his death, and they all came back.
有很多人都是从外地赶回来的
Many came from other towns.
也有从市里坐着小车来的
Some drove from the city.
村长说  最远的有从广州赶过来的
The mayor said some came from as far as Guangzhou.
还有几个人被风雪误在了半路上
Some tried, but didn't make it in time,
没有来得及
because of the snowstorm.
来得人大部分我都不认识
I didn't recognize many of them.
有的人比我大得多
Many were older than me.
我不知道他们都是父亲哪一年的学生
I don't know when my father taught them.
也不知道该怎样称呼他们
I didn't know how to address them.
村长说
Anyway, as the mayor said,
反正都是骆先生的学生嘛
they are all my father's students.
生子  这些钱还给你吧
Take this money back.
咋能都不要呢  不是说好了的吗
Why? Didn't you pay the men?
来的人都不要  就连拿钱雇的人也不要
They won't take it, not even the ones we hired.
就一分钱也不要
No one wants the money.
你还是收起来吧
Take it back.
按着母亲的意思
At my mother's request,
父亲就安葬在前井旁边
my father was buried next to the old well.
村里有了自来水  井就荒了
The village has running water now, so no one needs a well.
早就没人再挑水了
No one draws water from it now.
母亲说  在这儿
My mother says from this hill,
父亲可以天天看见学校
my father can look down on the school.
母亲还说  将来她也要跟父亲埋在一起
She asks to be buried next to him when the time comes.
办完父亲的后事
After my father's funeral,
村长特意来说起了盖学校的事儿
the mayor came to talk about rebuilding the school.
他说县里拨了款
The city has granted funds,
村里家家户户也都捐了钱
and the village families have donated money.
说乡亲们无论如何也要完成父亲的心愿
He says we must fulfill my father's wishes.
生子  你带回来的钱呢  给妈吧
Your money, give it to me.
村长  你看  这些钱都是我这几十年积攒的
Mayor, we've saved over the years.
你把它收起来盖学校吧
Take it to rebuild the school.
这咋好意思呢  你说  长余不在了
I can't take it.
这钱你一定得收下
With my husband gone, you have to take it.
那好  那我把这些钱先拿上
All right, I'll take it then.
咱们村  你们母子俩算第一份
You are the first, but surely not the last, to help.
明天我就要走了
I am leaving tomorrow.
母亲让我陪她再去一趟学校
Mother has asked me to go to the schoolhouse one last time.
母亲说  等下次我再回来时
My mother says the next time I come back,
这所小学校就看不到了
the school we know will be gone.
生子  你看这学校都几十年了
Your father helped build this school.
你爸就在这学校教书
He taught here so many years.
在这里比在家待得时间还长
Spent as much time here as at home.
长余  你都听到了吗
Changyu, can you hear me?
村长说了  要盖新学校
The mayor will rebuild the school.
按你的心愿去盖  盖一个高大  漂漂亮亮的
They'll build a tall
一个好学校
and wonderful school...
为了完成你的心愿  按你的意思去盖
just as you wished.
明年开春就动工了
They will start building next spring.
这回你放心了吧
You won't have to worry anymore.
新学校盖好了
When the school is completed,
我亲手织一块红挂上去
I will hang a lucky red banner there.
你就放心吧
You can rest easy now.
你看看你爸  实心实意
You know, your father was a sincere man.
整天跟我说  想叫你教书
He always wanted you to become a teacher,
接他的班
to take over for him.
把你送到师范学校念了
You went to the teachers' college,
一天书你也没教上
but you never taught a day of class.
哪怕你上一天课  教一天书
If you could teach for one day,
也是你爸爸这一片心都没有实现了
I think it would make him happy.
你就干别的工作去了
Then you can go back to your life.
你看  学校连上课的人都没有了
Look, there's no teacher now.
听不到孩子们念书的声音了
No sound of children reciting their lessons.
听村长说  过两天县上可能还会派个新老师来
The mayor said a new teacher was on the way.
新老师来
Not many teachers,
再上课也没有你爸爸声音好听啊  特别的响亮
would sound as good as your father.
四十多年我都没听够
After 40 years, I still love that voice.
好听呀  你爸读书
I can still hear it.
妈  我考虑好了
Mother, I've been thinking.
这次你跟我回城里  咱们一块儿住
Why don't you come to the city with me?
我不去
No, thank you.
有你爸在这儿  哪儿我也不去
I won't leave your father.
把你自己留在这儿  让我咋放心呢
How can I leave you here alone?
别为我担心
Don't worry about me.
我自己会照顾我自己的
I can take care of myself.
你在城里工作都好吧
Are you doing all right in the city?
好  妈
Yes.
特别好  你放心吧
Don't worry about me.
有女朋友吗
Do you have a girlfriend?
到时候再说吧
Let's not talk about it.
你看  你都那么大岁数了
You're not young anymore.
别挑剔了啊
Don't be so picky.
你听妈告诉你
Listen to me.
有合适的  自己找一个
Find yourself a nice girl
找一个领回来  让妈看看
and bring her home to meet me.
可是  你爸不在了
Your father's gone.
你爸呀  就为你这事担心
He used to worry about you.
儿女大了  拴不住了
Our children must leave home.
离爹娘远了  就看不到了
We can't keep you here forever.
做父母的
As parents...
儿女出了门  父母都担心呐  你看
we let you go, but we never stopped worrying.
你爸  一直
Your father...
都挂念你  记着你
...missed you so.
- 别哭了  妈    - 你看他
- Please don't cry.    - Your father...
你老哭老哭  你看你这身体都坏了
Mother, please don't cry.
你看他去了  把咱们母子留下  孤孤单单的
With your father gone, it's hard not to feel lonely.
好了
I know.
你呀
You...
在外面好好工作啊
...must work hard and make a good life.
能写会算  是件好事  念
"One must learn to read and write."
能写会算  是件好事
大事小情  提笔就记  念
"Keep a journal faithfully."
大事小情  提笔就记
知今知古  知天知地  念
"Know the present, know the past."
知今知古  知天知地
春夏秋冬  一年四季  念
"Spring, summer, fall, winter. Four seasons in a year."
春夏秋冬  一年四季
东西南北  四方天地  念
"East, West, South, North."
东西南北  四方天地
风霜雪雨  事事在意  念
"In everything there is a purpose."
风霜雪雨  事事在意
我一大早就让村长把学生们集合起来
I gathered the students early that morning.
我说我要给学生们上一节课
I told them I would teach them for one day.
村长问我为什么
The mayor asked me why.
我说我是为了母亲  也为了父亲
I said it was for my mother and for my father too.
我就站在父亲常站的那个地方
I stood in my father's place,
父亲在这儿站了一辈子
where he stood for so many years.
我想  此时此刻  父亲一定能听见
I felt sure he could hear my voice,
我和孩子们念书的声音吧
and those of the students.
我念的就是当年父亲在开学第一天念的那篇课文
The book I am using is the same one he used that first day.
其实这不是正式的课文
It is not a textbook.
这是父亲自己编的一段识字歌儿
It is a book he wrote himself.
能写会算  是件好事
"One must learn to read and write."
大事小情  提笔就记
"Keep a journal faithfully."
知今知古  知天知地
"Know the present, know the past."
春夏秋冬  一年四季
"Spring, summer, fall, winter. Four seasons in a year."
东西南北  四方天地
"East, West, South, North."
风霜雪雨  事事在意
"In everything there is a purpose."
长幼尊卑  敬重有序
"Know respect for your elders."
人生在世  要有志气
"In life, you must make goals."
剧 终
THE END